Guide to the Elsie H. Hillman Papers, 1920-2015 AIS.2013.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Elsie H. Hillman Papers
1920-2015
1952-2012
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Hillman, Elsie Hilliard
AIS.2013.02
84.3 Linear Feet (141 boxes)
The Elsie H. Hillman Papers document the life of Elsie Hillman (1925-2015), a prominent regional Republican Party activist and philanthropist. As early as 1952 she became involved in politics by campaigning for Dwight D. Eisenhower for president. She then became involved in the inner workings of the Republican Party at the local, state and national levels. Her leadership and diplomatic skills played a vital supporting role in the elections of politicians such as Governors Dick Thornburgh and Tom Ridge, Senator H. John Heinz III, State Treasurer Barbara Hafer and President George H.W. Bush. Additionally Hillman was involved in the local community through organizations such as the Hill House, UPMC, and WQED as well as involved in city affairs as a key member of the Pittsburgh Financial Leadership Commission. The collection contains a variety of materials including correspondence, meeting minutes, memoranda, reports, newspaper clippings, photographs, realia, and audio-video materials. The Elsie H. Hillman Website also provides an overview of her life and accomplishments with some digital reproductions of selected items.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of Elsie Hillman's speeches and remarks are available online.
Previous Citation
Elsie H. Hillman Papers, 1920-2015, AIS.2013.02, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Biography
Elsie Hilliard Hillman was widely recognized for her political leadership in the Republican Party and for her dedication to her hometown of Pittsburgh through both civic and philanthropic leadership.
Born Elsie Mead Hilliard on December 9, 1925 to Thomas Jones Hilliard (1894-1952) and Marianna Talbott (1897-1950) in Pittsburgh, Elsie's family lived in the neighborhood of Squirrel Hill, then later in the communities of Hampton Township and Fox Chapel. Her father was the president of the Waverly Oil Works Company and later became a vice president at U. S. Steel. Elsie was the fourth of five children born in the Hilliard family. Her siblings include: Mary Jones Hilliard Jackson (1919-1999), Thomas Jones Hilliard, Jr. (1921-2015), Harry Talbott Hilliard (1923-1993), and William Raymond Hilliard (1928-1990). She attended the Ethel Walker School (Simsbury, CT), graduated from the Ellis School (Pittsburgh, PA) in 1943, and then attended Westminster Choir College (Princeton, NJ).
Following her first year at Westminster, Elsie M. Hilliard married longtime friend of the family, Henry Lea Hillman, on May 12, 1945. Mr. Hillman, born in 1918, was serving in the United States Navy at the time of their marriage, and is the son of John Hartwell Hillman, Jr. (1880-1959) and Juliet Cummins Lea (1885-1940). The newlyweds resided in Texas, where Mr. Hillman was stationed. Elsie would not return to Westminster.
Like the Hilliards, members of the Hillman family were leaders in the business community. J. Hartwell Hillman headed his family company, J. H. Hillman & Sons, in partnership with his brothers Ernest Hillman (1883-1969) and James Frazier Hillman (1888-1972). The company operated as a coal, iron and steel brokerage, and later as owners of mining operations, barge lines, coke ovens and blast furnaces. Henry L. Hillman succeeded his father as head of the company by the late 1950s, and would transform and diversify its holdings. The business would be renamed "The Hillman Company," which would also include chemical production operations, sporting goods manufacturing, concrete pipe production, and the manufacturing of aircraft components. Mr. Hillman's prominent business interests have been closely associated with the Pittsburgh Coke and Chemical Company, National Steel Corporation and PNC Bank.
Following the war, Elsie and Henry Hillman would return to their native Pittsburgh to reside and rear a family. Their children are: Juliet Lea Hillman Simonds (1947), Audrey Hillman Fisher (1949), Henry L. Hillman, Jr. (1951), and William Talbott Hillman (1954).
Elsie began her political career as a campaign volunteer for Dwight D. Eisenhower's presidential campaign in 1952. During this campaign, she was noted for her use of a used car, commonly referred to as the "Ike-mobile," that was outfitted with a sound system, which she and other campaign volunteers drove throughout the city. Her name would be associated with numerous local, state, and national campaigns for the next five decades. In 1956 she was elected as Republican committee member of the 14th ward in the City of Pittsburgh. In 1964, she was elected as Chair of the Republican Committee of Allegheny County (RCAC) for the 14th Ward. In 1975, she became the National Committeewomen of the Republican Party and in 1978, she was elected to the Executive Committee of the Republican National Committee. She was also integral in the campaigns of numerous Republican candidates including Dick Thornburgh, Arlen Specter, Tom Ridge, H. John Heinz III, Barbara Hafer and Presidents Gerald R. Ford and George H.W. Bush, among others. While campaigns are highly visible events in the political arena, she was also the champion of several high profile causes and issues within the various levels of the Republican Party organization. These include greater inclusion of minorities and women in the Party and support of a women's right to choose in the abortion debate. Elsie also recognized the emergence of the "religious right" within the Party. Considering her position as a moderate Republican, she became interested in investigating the political shift that would cause.
Throughout Elsie Hillman's years guiding the Republican Party and their candidates, she became close personal friends with many candidates, their families and their staffs. Many of these relationships would extend beyond their years holding public office. These long term friendships would include Senator Hugh Scott, Senator H. John Heinz II, Governor Bill Scranton, Governor Dick Thornburgh, Governor Tom Ridge, President Gerald R. Ford and First Lady Betty Ford, and President George H. W. Bush and First Lady Barbara Bush.
For a detailed treatment of Elsie Hillman's political career, please consult the book, Never a Spectator: The Political Life of Elsie Hillman, by Kathy McCauley (2012).
In addition to her role in the Republican Party, Hillman has also been involved in a number of civic and philanthropic activities on both local and national levels. She maintained a long-term commitment to the well-being of her native Pittsburgh. She was appointed to serve as a member or chairperson of numerous local government boards, commissions, and tasks forces to study and guide a range of issues, including public education reform, entertainment revenue, Home Rule for Allegheny County, and the financial recovery of the City of Pittsburgh. Her public service also included many of Pittsburgh's non-profit social service and cultural agencies, such as the Hill House Association, the Urban League, the Pittsburgh AIDS Task Force, the Persad Center, the Pittsburgh Cultural Trust, the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra and WQED (Pittsburgh's public radio and television station). During the financial crisis of 2004-2005, the City of Pittsburgh made a financial decision to close the public pools. The "Save Our Summer" program was formed with Hillman as Co-Chair, which successfully raised funds to keep 16 neighborhood pools and recreation centers open. On the national stage, Elsie Hillman would serve on several White House commissions, commemoration planning groups, and preservation organizations.
An active member of Calvary Episcopal Church in Pittsburgh's East End, Elsie Hillman participated in several interfaith efforts, particularly in regard to a dialogue between the Christian and Jewish faith communities. Pittsburgh area colleges and universities have consistently been recipients of Elsie's interest and support. Mr. and Mrs. Hillmans' first major gift to the University of Pittsburgh led to the creation of Hillman Library, which was dedicated to the memory of James Hartwell Hillman, Jr. (WUP, Class of 1901) on September 6, 1968. Since that time, they have supported many educational programs at Pitt, including a 2014 gift of $5 million to the Institute of Politics, which will support the Civic Engagement Scholars Program. At Chatham University, the Hillmans were co-founders of the Pennsylvania Center for Women in Politics in 1998; later, the Elsie Hillman Chair of Women in Politics was established and reflects Elsie's commitment to gender equality and the empowerment of women to actively engage in the political sphere. Elsie Hillman also served on the Board of Trustees of Carlow University as a trustee emeritus; she was a strong supporter of the Grace Ann Geibel Institute for Justice and Social Responsibility.
In 2002, the Hillman Cancer Center opened on Center Avenue in the Shadyside neighborhood of Pittsburgh as the primary clinical service facility for the UPMC's Cancer Centers and the research center for the University of Pittsburgh's Cancer Institute (UPCI). Elsie Hillman served as the Co-Chair of the UPCI and UPMC Cancer Center Council.
The Hillman Family Foundation serves as an administrative and program office to coordinate the charitable giving of Mr. and Mrs. Hillman and their immediate family. As of 2014, there were 18 individual foundations included in the Hillman Family Foundation, which has provided over $21 million in funding of various projects that encompass Community and Economic Development, Cultural Advancement and the Arts, Education, Environmental and Conservation, Health and Medicine, Human and Social Service, and Religious causes.
Elsie H. Hillman died in Pittsburgh on August 4, 2015.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elsie H. Hillman on March 1, 2013.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 14 series:
I. Republican Party Activity, 1960-2000
II. Campaigns, 1952-2013
III. Other Political Activity, 1956-2012
IV. Community Involvement, 1946-2013
V. Speeches and Writings, 1973-2013
VI. Awards, 1964-2014
VII. Subject Files, 1970-2014
VIII. National Awareness, 1985-1993
IX. General Correspondence, 1964-2014
X. Personal (Friends and Family), 1939-2014
XI. Public Profiles, 1960-2009
XII. Photographs, c.1930s-2012
XIII. Realia, 1952-2004
XIV. Audio-Video Material, 1974-2012
Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government; Allegheny County (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Social action; Politics; Video recordings (physical artifacts); Sound recordings; Photographs; Personal papers; Newspapers; Civil rights; Political campaigns -- Pennsylvania; Political campaigns -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Political campaigns -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Political campaigns -- United States; Pro-choice movement; Religious right; Women's rights -- Pennsylvania; Women's rights -- United States; Heinz, John; Ford, Gerald R.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David); Bush, George, H.W (Herbert Walker); Bush, George Walker; Hillman, Henry L.; National Black Republican Council; Republican National Convention; Calvary Episcopal Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Blair House Restoration Foundation; President's Drug Advisory Council (U.S.); Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra; Pittsburgh Public Schools; Pittsburgh Cancer Institute; Pennsylvania Council of Republican Women; National Center for Voluntary Action; Hill House Association; Chatham University; Carlow College (Oakland, Pittsburgh, Pa.); WQED (Television station: Pittsburgh, Pa.); UPMC Health System; University of Pittsburgh; Republican Party (Pa.). State Committee; Republican Party (Pa.); Republican National Committee (U.S.); Republican Majority for Choice; Republican Leadership Council; Borge, Victor; Anstine, Anne; Bush, Barbara; Hillman family; Thornburgh, Dick; Specter, Arlen; Scranton, William Warren; Scott, Hugh; Powell, Colin L.; Ridge, Thomas J.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous); McClung, Elmer; Hillman, Elsie Hilliard; Hillman, Elsie Hilliard; Hafer, Barbara
- Republican Party Activity, 1960-2000; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, press releases, reports, and other materials pertaining to Elsie Hillman's activity in the Republican Party. This includes her time as Republican National Committeewoman, her activities at the Republican National Conventions from 1964 -2000, her involvement with the Pennsylvania Republican State Committee, and her political involvement at the local level. Additionally there are records relating to affiliated Republican organizations, the Pennsylvania Council of Republican Women, The Republican Leadership Council, and Hillman's own PAC, the Republican Future Fund.
  - Republican National Committee, 1975-2001; 1.
    Subseries 1 contains correspondence, subject files, newspaper clippings, reports, and other records pertaining to Elsie Hillman's activities with the Republican National Committee. Appointed in 1975, Hillman served as Republican National Committeewoman for Pennsylvania until 1996. During this time she was involved in multiple initiatives within the party including being a member of both the Standing Committee on Rules and the Subcommittee for Minority and Ethnic Participation. In addition to files detailing her activities within the Republican Party, there are a number of records which cover a particular topic of importance or interest as well as her retirement as Republican National Committeewoman in 1996.
    - Correspondence, 1975-2001
      - 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
      - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
      - 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Subject Files, 1971-1996
      - 18th National Republican Women's Convention Conference, Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 18th National Republican Women's Convention, Memoranda and Guest Lists, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 18th National Republican Women's Convention, Press Releases and Mailings, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - 18th National Republican Women's Convention, Related Conference Materials, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Appointment to National Committee, Congratulatory Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Appointment to National Committee, Newspaper Clippings, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Atwater, Lee, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Baker, Howard, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Baker, Jim, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Ban on Gays in the Military, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Budget and State Election Reports, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Crisp, Mary, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Demographic Shift Research, 1984-1998 (Box 1, Folder 20-22)
      - Directory of National, State, and Local Personnel, c. 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Election '88 Kick-Off, Event Binder Materials, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2-5)
      - Election '88 Kick-Off, Voter Incentive Project, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Election Reform, Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Electoral Gains and Losses, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Equal Rights Amendment Boycott, Newspaper Clipping, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Fact Sheet, Women in the Republican Party, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Flat Tax Reform, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Fundraising Group List, c.1970s (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Gerrymandering, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - GOP Development, Newspaper Clippings, Newsletters, and Magazine Articles, 1976-1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Halloween Love Project, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Highlights of the Reagan Administration, Briefing Book, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - International Coalitions, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Jesse Jackson and PUSH, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Laxalt, Paul, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Lincoln Day Packet, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Lincoln Day, Notes, c. 1970s (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Lott, Trent, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Memoranda, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Memoranda, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Moderate Republicans, Magazine Articles, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, Pittsburgh AIDS Clinical Trials Unit, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Newspaper Clipping on Placement on Ballot for National Committee, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - North American Free Trade Act, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Notes, On Women Candidates, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Operation Open Door, Press and Memoranda, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Panama Canal, Memorandum on Panama Canal Resolution, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Panama Canal, Newspaper Article Packets, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Panama Canal, Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Panama Canal, Reports, Research, and Related texts, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Panama Canal, Republican Mailings and Writings, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Political Action Committees and Campaign Finance Reform, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Reagan, Maureen, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Republican Biography of Hillman, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Republican Moderates, Articles and Strategic Goals, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Republican National Committee Advisory Councils Committee Directories, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Republican National Committee Northeast Meeting, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Republican National Finance Committee, Invitation to Serve on Women's Committee, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Republican National Leadership Conference, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Republican Party History Pamphlets, 1956-1980s (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Republican Party Pamphlets, 1970s-1978 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Republican Spirit Booklet, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Republican Women's Leadership Forum, Schedule of Events, c. 1980s (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Ripon Society, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Ripon Society, "A Free Zone for the West Bank", 1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Ripon Society Forum, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Rumsfeld, Donald, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Ryan White Care Act and AIDS Funding, Letters of Support Written to Congress, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Schweiker, Richard, Newsletters and Bulletins, 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Schweiker, Richard, Newsletters and Bulletins, 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Speech Cards, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Speech notes, On the Republican National Committee, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Tax Law Reform, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Team 100, Issues Survey, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Thousand Points of Light, Conceptual Documents, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Thousand Points of Light, Points of Light Booklets, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Thousand Points of Light, Requests for Points of Light Considerations, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Transformation in American politics Study, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Whittlesey, Faith Ryan, 1977-1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Winter Meeting Materials, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Women Who Win Workshop, Slideshow Script, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Women Who Win Workshop, Workshop Guide, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
    - Standing Committee on Rules, 1975-1988
      - Committee Membership Roster, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Draft, Chapter of Book "Party Rules", 1984 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Draft, Rule No. 32, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Final Report of the Select Committee on Contests, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Final Report of the Standing Committee on the Rules of the Republican Party, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1983-1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Memoranda, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Memoranda, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Memoranda, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Notes, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Notes and Articles, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Party Rules and Platform Pamphlets, 1970s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Press Releases and Pamphlets, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Proposed Rules as Recommended by the Standing Committee, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Remarks and Testimonials, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Rules Committee Resolutions and Drafts, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Subcommittee for Minority and Ethnic Participation, 1981-1988
      - Black PAC, Letter concerning support for Jesse Helms, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Final Reports of the Subcommittee on Minority and Ethnic Participation, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Freedom Republicans, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - Interview Questions, c. 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Motion by Elsie Hillman to Create an Advisory Committee, c. 1985-1987 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - National Hispanic Assembly, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Newspaper Clippings, Articles, and Research Materials, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Notes, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Polling Data and Minority Subcommittee Questionnaire, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Publication, Black Politics 1980: A Guide to the Republican National Convention (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Publication, Ethnic Voters and National Issues: Coalitions in the 1980s, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Publication, Tax Welfare and Policy Options: Implications for Minorities and the Poor, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Resolution Establishing Subcommittee, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Report on Redistricting, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - RNC News Liaison News Summary, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Survey, Joint Center for Political Studies Survey on Black Political Attitudes, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Retirement as Republican National Committeewoman, 1995-1996
      - Correspondence, A-B, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      - Correspondence, C-D, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence, E-G, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence, H-K, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, L-O, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, P-S, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence, T-Z, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, Unidentified, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Elsie Hillman Breakfast, Attendees List, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Elsie Hillman Breakfast, Breakfast Tickets and Tables Sold Lists, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Elsie Hillman Breakfast, Correspondence and Notes, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Elsie Hillman Breakfast, Host Committee List, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Elsie Hillman Breakfast, Invitation, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Elsie Hillman Breakfast, Program Planning Memoranda, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Elsie Hillman Breakfast, Table Arrangements and Potential Host Committee Members, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Letter announcing decision not to seek another term as RNC Committeewoman, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 13)